Guide to the Lauren Pond photographs, 2011-2016 RL.11506
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lauren Pond photographs
2011-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Pond, Lauren
RL.11506
.5 Linear Feet 2 boxes; 49 prints
Collection consists of 49 color inkjet prints from the documentary project Test of Faith by photographer Lauren Pond. The images are approximately 20x14 inches in size and are unmatted. Between 2011 and 2016, Pond documented the life, death, and West Virginian family of Pentecostal pastor and serpent handler, Mack Wolford, of the Full Gospel Apostolic House of the Lord Jesus in Matoaka, West Virginia. The series includes images of Wolford's death in his family home after he was bitten by the venomous snake. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
The prints are arranged in their body of work in chronological order as received.
Biographical Note
Lauren Pond is a documentary photographer based in Ohio.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Lauren Pond photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2017.
Content Description
This collection consists of 49 color inkjet prints from the documentary project Test of Faith by photographer Lauren Pond. The images measure approximately 20x14 inches and are unmatted. Between 2011 and 2016, Pond documented the life, death, and West Virginian family of Pentecostal pastor and serpent handler, Mack Wolford, of the Full Gospel Apostolic House of the Lord Jesus in Matoaka, West Virginia. The series includes images of Wolford's death in his family home after he was bitten by the venomous snake.
In an artist's statement, Pond writes: "Serpent handlers, also known as Signs Followers, belong to a small Appalachian Pentecostal Holiness sect that holds a literal interpretation of the King James Bible's Mark 16:17-18. This passage describes the 'signs' of true believers, including the ability to 'take up serpents.' Believing in absolute obedience to God's Word, Signs Followers handle venomous snakes during their worship services. If bitten, they generally do not seek medical treatment, and instead, entrust their fate to God."
"Seeking a deeper understanding of serpent handlers and their faith, in 2011, Lauren traveled to West Virginia and met Mack, who invited her to document both his worship services and daily life. The course of her work changed dramatically in 2012, when she attended a worship service where Mack was fatally bitten by a rattlesnake. Through her images, Lauren illustrates her relationship with Mack and his family, the challenging experiences they have shared, and the insights these have given her into the tenets of the Signs Following faith – namely, forgiveness and renewal."
Test of Faith is the 2016 winner of Honickman First Book Prize in Photography, given by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Clergy -- Family relationships -- West Virginia; Death -- Photographs; Documentary photography -- West Virginia; Pentecostal churches -- Appalachian Region; Serpents -- Religious aspects -- Christianity; Snake cults (Holiness churches) -- West Virginia -- Photographs; Appalachian Region -- Religious life and customs -- Pictorial works.; West Virginia -- Religious life and customs; Color photographs; Inkjet prints; Color prints (photographs); Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Full Gospel Apostolic House of the Lord Jesus (Matoaka, W. Va.); Wolford, Mack; International Pentecostal Holiness Church
- Test of Faith: Signs, Serpents, Salvation, 2011-2016; 1; 49 prints 2 boxes
  - Old Yeller, Panther Park, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0001)
  - Pastor Mack Wolford's rattlesnake slithers around his neck during an outdoor worship service, Panther Park, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0002)
  - Mack with Old Yeller, Panther Park, West Virginia, 2011; 14 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0003)
  - Pearl Dawson, Mack's mother-in-law; Vicie "Snook" Haywood, his mother; and Chris Wolford, his brother, Panther Park, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0004)
  - Mack at an outdoor worship service, Panther Park, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0005)
  - Church of the Lord Jesus, Jolo, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0006)
  - Mack and parishioners during a homecoming worship service, Jolo, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0007)
  - Mack with Harvey Payne, pastor of the Church of the Lord Jesus, Jolo, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0008)
  - Mack in his church, the Full Gospel Apostolic House of the Lord Jesus, Matoaka, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0009)
  - Mack at his and his wife, Fran's, home, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0010)
  - Mack and Fran's kitchen, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0011)
  - Snook and Mack at Bible study at Snook's house, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0012)
  - Serpents in Mack and Fran's spare bedroom, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0013)
  - Mack at home with his morning coffee, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0014)
  - Mack on a serpent hunt during a documentary film shoot, near Jolo, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0015)
  - Mack on his way to Bible study, Fran in the background, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2011; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0016)
  - 2:16 p.m.: Snook, Panther Park, West Virginia, May 27, 2012; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0017)
  - 2:20 p.m.: Mack with Old Yeller just after the snake bit him, Panther Park, West Virginia, 2012; 19 3/8 x 13 7/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0018)
  - 2:21 p.m.: Jamie Lloyd with Snook, Mack, and Old Yeller, Panther Park, West Virginia, 2012; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0019)
  - 2:27 p.m., Panther Park, West Virginia, 2012; 20 1/2 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11506-P-0020)
  - 2:42 p.m., Panther Park, West Virginia, 2012; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0021)
  - 3:00 p.m., Panther Park, West Virginia, 2012; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0022)
  - 3:03 p.m., Panther Park, West Virginia, 2012; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0023)
  - 6:33 p.m.: Jason Stone with Mack at Pearl's house, Brushfork, West Virginia, 2012; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0024)
  - 6:21 p.m.: Snook with Mack at Pearl's house, Brushfork, West Virginia, 2012; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0025)
  - 10:50 p.m.: Snook; Robin Wolford-Brandon, Mack's sister; and Elijah Wood, Mack's nephew, Brushfork, West Virginia, 2012; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0026)
  - Anniversary service at the Full Gospel Apostolic House of the Lord Jesus, Matoaka, West Virginia, 2013; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0027)
  - The Full Gospel Apostolic House of the Lord Jesus, one year after Mack's death, Matoaka, West Virginia, 2013; 19 7/8 x 13 7/8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0028)
  - Old Yeller in Snook's spare bedroom, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2013; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0029)
  - Snook, Bramwell, West Virginia, 2013; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0030)
  - Snook with a customer at the Bramwell Café, Bramwell, West Virginia, 2013; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0031)
  - Elijah playing Mack's songs for Mack's niece Amber McLaughlin, Robin, and Fran after Thanksgiving dinner, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2014; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0032)
  - Elijah and Amber, Bramwell, West Virginia, 2013; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0033)
  - Jason and Snook with serpents, Matoaka, West Virginia, 2013; 20 3/4 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11506-P-0034)
  - Foot washing at a worship service, Big Stone Gap, Virginia, 2016; 19 7/8 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0035)
  - Mack's brother Kevin Wolford and Old Yeller at Snook's house, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2014; 20 3/8 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11506-P-0036)
  - Fran at home, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2014; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0037)
  - Mack's guitar at Fran's house, 2014; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0038)
  - Pearl, Brushfork, West Virginia, 2016; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0039)
  - Fran picking corn at her father and stepmother's house, Brushfork, West Virginia, 2016; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0040)
  - On the porch at Snook's house, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2016; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0041)
  - Family gathering at Snook's house, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2016; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0042)
  - Snook in her living room, Bluefield, West Virginia, 2016; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0043)
  - Brushfork, West Virginia, 2016; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0044)
  - Worship service at the Wolfords' new church, the House of Prayer in the Name of the Lord Jesus, where Chris is pastor, Squire, West Virginia, 2016; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0045)
  - Chris with Michael McLaughlin, Amber's husband, Squire, West Virginia, 2016; 20 1/2 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11506-P-0046)
  - Chris walking on a serpent, Squire, West Virginia, 2016; 20 x 14 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0047)
  - Snook, Robin, and Elijah, Squire, West Virginia, 2016; 20 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11506-P-0048)
  - Snook, Squire, West Virginia, 2016; 14 x 20 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11506-P-0049)